<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief and perfect journal of the late preceedings and successe of the English army in the West-Indies, continued until June the 24th 1655. Together with some quæres inserted and answered. Published for satisfaction of all such who desire truly to be informed in these particulars. / By I.S. an eye-witnesse.</title>
            <author>I. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S35</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E853_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8777</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873397</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873397</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168318</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93183)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168318)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 129:E853[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief and perfect journal of the late preceedings and successe of the English army in the West-Indies, continued until June the 24th 1655. Together with some quæres inserted and answered. Published for satisfaction of all such who desire truly to be informed in these particulars. / By I.S. an eye-witnesse.</title>
                  <author>I. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [i.e. 29], [1]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 15 and 16 repeated in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e. September] 25]".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>West Indies --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168318:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A brief and perfect JOURNAL OF The late Proceedings and Succeſſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army in the <hi>WEST-INDIES,</hi> Continued until <hi>June</hi> the 24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1655.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH <hi>Some Quaeres inſerted and Anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed for ſatisfaction of all ſuch who deſire truly to be informed in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. S.</hi> an Eye-witneſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Veritas nudata celari non poteſt.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:168318:2"/>
            <head>A brief and perfect Journal of the late Proceedings and Succeſſe of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Army in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued until <hi>June</hi> the <hi>24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1655.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all Records, ancient or modern (of the actions and tranſactions of Kingdoms and Nations) there is not to be ſeen more ſuitable ſucceſſes atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ſtrange and occult proceedings, then late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> and although the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of ſo grand affairs (and matters of high concernment) were committed to ſome who had the repute of being well principled, valiant and politick in War, yet there wanted not means to fruſtrate the deſign, (and expectations of moſt men) the particulars whereof I ſhall deliver in as brief and true manner as poſſibly I may; but before I proceed further, it will not be amiſſe to inſert theſe Queries with their Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether or not the ſetting forth of this Army were real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended for the glory of God, and propagation of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether thoſe that were of this Army were fit inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be imployed in the exaltation of Gods work, and pulling down of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And laſtly, whether the hand of Almighty God hath not been plain and manifeſtly ſeen in oppoſition to their actings and proceedings.</p>
            <p>To the firſt is anſwered, That after divers ſerious debates and reſults (<hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi>) it was at length reſolved (by the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168318:2"/>Authority and Councell of State) to ſend an Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Weſtern-Indies:</hi> what preparation was made, is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to moſt of the Nation; but for what or againſt whom, was ſcarſe underſtood by any (except ſome few ſuperiors) and for this cauſe divers conſcientious men (who preferred the ſervice of God, before that of men; and treaſure in Heaven, beyond riches and honour on Earth) ſcrupled the deſign, and deſerted the ſervice: For what zealous heart would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly embrace an unknown enterpriſe, which might perhaps tend to his own deſtruction ſooner then his Enemies, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring to pull that down which God hath ſet up, and to ſet up that which he never called him unto? Shall a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude periſh through means of ſome few particular men, (in fulfilling that proverb) by pinning their faith on others ſleeves? hath not God conferred as much of the gifts of grace and nature on the mean men of the world, as on thoſe of the greateſt rank and dignity? doth honour adde zeal, riches, valour? or have the moſt eminent in office and command, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the greateſt eminency of wiſdome and conduct? certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we have found otherwiſe, for oftentimes ſuch involve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in eminent and irrecoverable dangers, nor is it alwaies pregnancy of wit, valour and diſcretion (although theſe be famous in war) that gives the victory, but God that worketh all in all, and who can ſay, What doſt thou?</p>
            <p>To conclude the deſign to be altogether grounded on a wrong and corrupt principle, were to accuſe our Grandees with folly, irreligion, and what not; when indeed it is beyond the ability of man to pry into the ſecret thoughts and intents of the heart, 'tis only the Almighty can do it; and although there may be a probable conjecture given of the intent of the workman, by the inſtrument he taketh in hand, yet God hath been ſometimes pleaſed to make the wicked, inſtruments of good; but it doth not therefore follow, that ſuch ſhould be imployed in good works, neither the ſervants of God in bad; all created things move in their proper ſphere; the natural man acts in his natural function, and mindeth onely the things of the world; and the ſpiritual man (although he be in the world) is not of the world, but mindeth the things of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168318:3"/>the Spirit, and the fulfilling of the glory of God, whoſe power and juſtice is as well ſeen in the deſtruction of the wicked, as preſervation of the righteous.</p>
            <p>Now to return to the good intent of the Cauſe whereof I treat, if we reflect upon the conſequence of actions, it will ſoon appear, there was nothing leſſe aimed at, then Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and eſtabliſhment of the Goſpel, nor nothing more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted, then gain to themſelves, and eſtabliſhment in the rich poſſeſſions of others; but ſervants often diſobey the command of their Maſters, and act contrary to his will and pleaſure, 'tis poſſible it might be ſo now, and that might cauſe their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter puniſhment.</p>
            <p>If we look upon this expedition in reference to the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof (as it is in it ſelf) we may finde (by theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſiderations) that it was both lawful, juſt, and warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by the Word of God, and Law of Nations. Firſt, in regard thoſe they went out againſt were Idolaters, Hereticks, and Members of the falſe Church. Secondly, For that they (ſome years ſince) moſt wickedly and inhumanely murthered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed divers of our Nation that traded peaceably with them in the <hi>Weſt-Indies.</hi> Thirdly, There was no breach of League in the proſecution of this War, there being no Articles of peace or ceſſation in force betwixt both Nations, to the ſouthward of the Tropick. Laſtly, Conqueſt is free to all people, no Law of Nations can prohibit the power of the Sword, 'tis only God that ſets its bounds and limits, and where his pleaſure is, it ſhould make a final conqueſt, there is it free inheritance to the Conqueror, and his ſucceſſors. By that power did the <hi>Normans</hi> invade and conquer <hi>England,</hi> ſince which time there hath no leſſe then 25. Kings and Queens ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively (although not ſucceſſefully) reigned: by the ſame power was there lately a period put to that government, and a new eſtabliſhed: by this power had the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> been ſubject to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and by the ſame power again recovered; by this power are the <hi>Turks</hi> and Infidels (at this day) poſſeſſors of the beſt and fruitfulleſt parts of the earth; and by the ſame power <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came conqueror of the whole world; Many and incredible are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168318:3"/>the difficulties and admirable exploits run through and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by this power, and that ſometimes by a weak hand, for when the Omnipotent puniſheth the wicked, and correcteth his own people, he often maketh choice of one and the ſame means to be inſtrumental for both.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the legality of the cauſe by which we muſt not meaſure the good intent; if we do, we may deceive our ſelves, for as hath been ſaid, the very actions and deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Army was ſuch, that no good at all might be expected from them, either in their intent or proceeding: To condemn all, becauſe many were guilty, were an act of much injuſtice, ſome might be better principled, otherwiſe of all Armies were they moſt miſerable, but the byaſs of riches and honours many times carrieth men headlong to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>A Common-wealth of people, is as mans body, ſome mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber may be corrupted, and yet the vitals preſerved, and the head not impaired; in ſuch caſes the skilful Chirurgeon, that takes care to keep and preſerve the Microcoſm, diſmembreth that part from the reſt of the body, that might otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the whole fabrick.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are called unto high places, (and beare rule and dominion over Nations) ought not only to be repleat with true zeal and wiſdome, but alſo valour and State policy, that ſo the gifts of Grace and Nature being united, they may (as pious Patrons, and good Chirurgeons) preſerve the body of the Nation, in ſpiritual and temporal health.</p>
            <p>God hath already begun a good work amongſt us, and let not <hi>England</hi> now deſpair of ſuch a Governor, there are yet ſome conſequences to be ſhewn, that the primary intents of our Grandees, were nothing ſutable to the following actings, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſactings of this Army. Grapes could not be expected from thornes, nor figs from thiſtles, but rather that the bad tree ſhould be cut down and caſt into the ſire. <hi>England</hi> is now very populous, and the abundance of fruitleſſe trees ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumber the vines, that they cannot fructifie; the late Civill war hath yet left ſome ſpecies of malignancy, the ſores and corruptions of the Nation are not healed, becauſe not clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for the tincture of ungodlineſs is yet ſavoury in their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168318:4"/>palats; men of deſperate fortunes have deſperate means of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; they ſubſiſt not by ſweat of their own brow, but reap the fruit of others labors, ſowing the ſeed of ſedition, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable wickedneſs in a Land where they have no right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; Can a Chriſtian Common-wealth flouriſh either in godlineſs, plenty, or peace, when it abounds with ſuch profane vile caterpillers, and corrupters of all good manners? Is it not juſtice in God, and wiſdome in man to expell ſuch unworthy and unwelcome gueſts from among his people? <hi>Ireland</hi> hath already a ſufficient ſhare, and <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> (with the reſt of thoſe ſmall Iſlands, ſubject to this Dominion, who were wont to be a receptacle for ſuch vermin) are now ſo filled, that they vomit forth of their ſuperfluities into other places.</p>
            <p>Could there be a leſſe cruel, and more juſt means uſed then to imploy ſuch in a Forain War? the <hi>Indies</hi> are ſpacious, pleaſant and rich, too rich indeed for either the vicious inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, or no leſſe vicious invaders. But thoſe whom <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſent forth on this firſt expedition, were not many, their number was compleated elſewhere, and the deſign being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced with much ſecreſie (even to the Members of the Army it ſelf) manifeſtly argueth what they were which were inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for that ſervice; even ſuch who willingly proceeded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they knew not whither.</p>
            <p>That which now remaineth, is the proof of the Cauſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther really intended for Gods glory, and propagation of the Goſpel (as was firſt propounded) The arguments and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences conducing to the confirmation hereof, are briefly comprehended in this, That if it had pleaſed God in mercy (for the righteous ſake) to proſper the proceedings of the wicked, and to give the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and their rich poſſeſſions into the hands of thoſe who were more ſinful then themſelves, that then there would be a fair gap opened for the enriching divers good people of the Nation, and utter extirpation of all idle, profane and irreligious ones that ſhould be ſent over as ſouldiers and ſervants into this new conquered Common-wealth, that ſo, (all impediments being removed) the glory of God (above all things elſe) might be exalted, and the Goſpel have free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and recourſe throughout the Dominions.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168318:4"/>
            <p>Secondly, whether the inſtruments were ſutable to the work, hath been in part already reſolved, but more fully will appear in the following Journal, wherein is declared what and whence they were that acted, alſo what and where their actions were from time to time, together with the manner of ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>In the whole written Word of God may not be ſeen in any one inſtance, that ever he employed thoſe of his people (in his intended work and ſervice) which remained polluted in their ſins and wickedneſs, but alwaies firſt brought them (by ſome means or other) unto true humiliation and repentance; and this was ſometimes performed by gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g part of them over to be deſtroyed of their enemies: in which is ſeen (that by Gods permiſſion) good is ſometimes acted by means of the wicked; good conſequences may be drawn from bad ſubjects, as in the former ſenſe; but that ever ſuch ſhould perſevere in any good or godly work (as to the compleating thereof) is not only very improbable, but impoſſible, for that which is divided againſt it ſelf, cannot ſtand: humane reaſon will alſo tell us that any rare and curious piece of work cannot be performed by dull and unfit inſtruments.</p>
            <p>But to return to the reſolutions of the third and laſt Quaere, That the hand of God hath been plain and manifeſtly ſeen in oppoſition to their actions, doth not only appear in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſucceſs, but alſo of proceeding, and that in ſo miraculous a manner, that ſcantly any age may parallel; God indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds the counſels of the high and mighty, and turneth their wiſdome into meer fooliſhneſs: That an Army ſo numerous, ſtrong and well provided, ſhould be ſo cow'd out, beaten, and ſhamefully repulſed, by leſſe then a handful of men, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, was certainly the work of God, and it is marvellous in our eyes. O that men could be ſenſible of the guilt of ſin, and humble themſelves by repentance before deſtruction ſweep them hence that they be no more ſeen; or that they could take enſample by the deſtruction of others to perſiſt no longer in the waies of wickedneſs! But ſuch was the obdurate hearts, and ſeared conſciences of this people, that neither bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings nor curſings could mollifie; the golden Calf was already ſet up in their hearts, and although <hi>Aaron</hi> were preſent with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168318:5"/>them, yet there wanted a <hi>Moſes</hi> to deſtroy it, and ſupplicate the Almighty to avert his juſt judgements from a people that were ſo exceeding ſinfull.</p>
            <div type="journal">
               <p>
                  <hi>Now followeth the Journall it ſelf, wherein is deſcribed each proceeding and action in due place as they happened (with all things pertinent thereunto). Whereby the judicious and impartiall Readers may at leaſure give that ſolid and juſt construction of each particular matter according as the juſtneſſe or unjuſtneſſe of the cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, which probably (through haſt, multiplicity of buſineſſe, and a troubled ſpirit) I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have ſo well performed in reſolution to the former Quaeres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AFter it was abſolutely reſolved to ſend an Army into the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> preparations were accordingly made as well by Land as Sea; the Generals appointed for both were his Excellency <hi>Rob. Venables,</hi> and the Right Honourable <hi>William Pen;</hi> (men who had ſeen much of Gods actings for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in going in and out before them to their deliverance, and crowning their endevours with many glorious and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Victories) Divers good Ships and Friggots were allotted for this ſervice, (had they been but as well Victualed and Manned) and all Seamen that were willing to proceed in the ſervice, received entertainment; but for want of a due complement, many Freſh-water Sailors, and others, were preſt. Drums were alſo beaten up for ſuch Voluntary Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as were willing to ſerve the Common-wealth beyond Sea; which gave encouragement to ſeverell who go by the name of Hectors, and Knights of the blade, with common Cheats, Theeves, Cutpurſes and ſuch like leud perſons, who had long time lived by the ſleight of hand, and dexterity of wit, and were now making a fair progreſſe unto <hi>Newgate,</hi> from whence they were to proceed towards <hi>Tiborn;</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the dangerouſneſſe of that paſſage, very politickly directed their courſe another way, and became Souldiers for the State. Some ſloathfull and theeviſh ſervants likewiſe (to avoid the puniſhment of the Law, and coveting a yet more idle life) followed after in the ſame path; there was alſo drawn forth out of moſt of the old ſtanding Regiments, (ſuch as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168318:5"/>were newly enliſted) to compleat the number. For thoſe who were better principled, and knew what fighting was, were (as it ſhould ſeem) reſerved for a better purpoſe, ſome few only excepted, which were as a mixture of little wine with much water, the one loſing its proper ſtrength and vigor, and the other thereby little imbettered. And thus went on the preparation by Land whilſt the Ships were Rigging, Victualling and Manning; the generall Randevow for the Navy and Army was at <hi>Portſmouth</hi> and thereabouts; where (by the 10. of <hi>November,</hi> 1654.) moſt of the Ships were arrived, and ſuch proportions of Victuall and other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ordered to be compleated, as each Veſſell could conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently ſtore; ſome that was defective was alſo exchanged, notwithſtanding there remained much in the Fleet. There likewiſe the Sailors and Souldiers received ſome wages for better encouragement before their departure.</p>
               <p>On the 18. of <hi>December</hi> following, divers Companies of Souldiers were ſhipped, and the Rear Admirall (having or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) ſet ſail accordingly with his Squadron the next day. Within few dayes after followed the Generals with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Fleet and land Army, conſiſting in all of about 3000 men, divided into five Regiments, beſides Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, Treaſurers and other Officers of the States. The next Randevow appointed, was the Iſland of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it pleaſed God to grant them a fair paſſage and ſafe arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, and that within four dayes one of another, ſo that the whole Fleet being about 30. ſail, (one half being Victua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers) were riding together in <hi>Calile Bay</hi> by the firſt day of <hi>February,</hi> there remaining behind only two Ships of the Common-wealths (the Great and Little <hi>Charity</hi>) which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved afterwards prejudiciall to the Army, in their proceeding, not only in reſpect of the proper ſignification of their names, (which indeed in that ſenſe were both wanting) but qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their loading, the one being ordered to carry Morter Pieces, Granado ſhels, and ſtore of other Ammunition, and the other, Horſes with Armes and furniture for Horſemen; but through what intent or policy they were left in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> more then an ordinary capacity cannot apprehend, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168318:6"/>although expedition be ſaid to be the life of Action, yet though inconſiderate raſhneſſe, many a gallant Deſigne and Action are meerly overthrown.</p>
               <p>Immediately after the arrivall of the Fleet (as aforeſaid) the Souldiers were all put on ſhoar, and diſtributed into ſeverall quarters on the Iſland, where they had allowed ſuch diet as the Country afforded (which was none of the worſt.) The Carpenters of each Ship were ordered to ſet up thoſe Shallops with expedition which were brouhgt over in quarters out of <hi>England;</hi> and all the Coopers were buſied in trimming and fitting of water casks. In mean ſeaſon, two Frigots with a Commiſſioner and others were diſpatched to the Iſlands of <hi>Chriſtophers</hi> and <hi>Meaves,</hi> for the raiſing of as many Volunteers there as was thought convenient; neither were the Colonels and other Officers at <hi>Barbadoes</hi> negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in compleating their Regiments and Companies, and raiſing new: the Iſlanders likewiſe contributed of free coſt to ſet forth a troop of gallant Horſe, for the furtherance of this ſervice, the carcaſſes whereof were afterwards (at the Iſland of <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi>) either eaten for want of other food, or there left behind for the uſe of the enemy. During the aboad of the Fleet at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> divers <hi>Dutch</hi> Veſſels (near 20. in number) were made prize, whereof ſome were there found at Anchor, others the Frigots that were a cruſing at Sea, brought in, and that in regard they preſumed to traffick thither with ſuch commodities as were prohibited by the late Articles of peace concluded betwixt both Nations. The Victuallers taken was imployed to the uſe of the Navy, and the Veſſels for tranſportation of Souldiers.</p>
               <p>It's alſo remarkable, that in this mean time, there was an order for all Boyes belonging to the Fleet, (although not ſupernumeraries) to be cancelled out of the States Books, and for the future not to have any allowance of dyet, or wages, notwithſtanding there was no care taken for their tranſportation homewards, or diſpoſall otherwiſe, they ſtill remaining in the Ships, became burthenſome to thoſe on whom they had dependency, in participating of ſuch Victuall as they had ſparingly allowed for themſelves, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168318:6"/>the hand of providence (as it ſhould ſeem) willing in part to eaſe them of this burthen, a Sharke fiſh devoured at one time two youths belonging to a States ſhip, as they were ſwimming near the Veſſell; all that may be attributed to the good intent of this rigorous order, was for the better Husbanding of vitall proviſions, and to prolong the time of Victualling, but this, (with other matters) if it be not treaſon to ſpeak it) might have been more ſeaſonably performed at home.</p>
               <p>The new Shallops being lanched, and the Fleet furniſhed with freſh water and other neceſſaries, were in a readineſſe to depart, the field Army was alſo drawn down and ſhipped, they being now ſo numerous, that each Ships ſhare were as many as they could well carry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> the 31. they ſet ſail from that Iſland, and within two dayes paſſed betwixt the Iſlands of <hi>Martenico</hi> and <hi>Sancta L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſia,</hi> where they anchored that night; the day following they weighed from thence, and paſſing by the ſmall Iſlands of <hi>Dominica, Guardo Lupo, Monſerat</hi> and <hi>Meaves;</hi> the 6. of <hi>Aprill</hi> came by the <hi>Lee</hi> under <hi>Chriſtophers,</hi> where thoſe Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Souldiers that came off from that Iſland, and the next adjacent, were already ſhipped in prizes there taken, and awaited only the motion of the Fleet, the number of theſe were about 1300. which together with the other <hi>Barbarians</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> men of <hi>Barbadoes</hi>) compleated 5000. beſides Women and Children, whom (out of ill grounded confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and high preſumption) they had brought along with them, which made them ſeem rather as a people that went to inhabit ſome Country already conquered, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer: but for this perhaps they had too good a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
               <p>What manner of Souldiers theſe Planters proved, may ſoon be imagined, for if we look with an impartiall eye, upon the major part of thoſe that came out of <hi>England</hi> to be (as indeed they were) raw Souldiers, Vagabonds, Robbers and runagate ſervants, certainly theſe Iſlanders muſt be the very ſcum of ſcums, and meer dregs of corruption, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168318:7"/>ſuch upon whoſe endevours, it was impoſſible to expect a bleſſing.</p>
               <p>But to return to the Fleet, who now ſhaped their courſe towards the Iſland of <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> conceiving it requiſite to reduce that by the way, as well for refreſhment of the Army, as to keep men in action untill (the long expected) arrivall of more Granado ſhels, and Morter pieces, there being only one in the Fleet, beſides ſome woodden ones, lately made, which were deemed unfit for ſo great an enterpriſe as was intended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aprill</hi> the 8. they paſſed by <hi>Sanct 1 Cruſe,</hi> and the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing was ordered to be obſerved (throughout the Fleet) as a day of Humiliation for the good ſucceſſe of the Army, but one day was not effectuall for the humbling of thoſe who had remained ſo many years obdurate in wickedneſſe. The next Iſland was that of <hi>Saint John,</hi> and having gained the length of the Weſter end thereof, the dtſtance to <hi>Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niola</hi> was 22. Leagues.</p>
               <p>The Colonels and other Officers were now ordered to get their men in readineſſe to land, and to augment the number, there was drawn forth a Regiment of rugged Sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, whoſe manners argued them better fed then either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the principles of Chriſtian Religion, or rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of marſhall diſcipline.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aprill</hi> the 13. they came fair by the Iſland and plainly diſcovered the Town of <hi>Domingo,</hi> and after ſome conſultation had (with the pretended Pilots and guides) for the better landing, and conduct of the Army to the Town) the Land Generall, with a Squadron of Ships, 7000 foot Souldiers, a Troop of Horſe, and three dayes proviſion of Victuall) went farther to leeward and landed (the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing) in ſafety, ſome ten leagues to the Weſtward of the Town.</p>
               <p>No ſooner were they all landed (having no oppoſition) but they began to promiſe to themſelves mountains of gold, nothing buſied their minds and thoughts more, then the riches of the place, their talke was all of the money, plate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168318:7"/>and gallant plunder they were like to have; but they were ſoon taken off from theſe vain hopes, Proclamation being then made (in the head of the Army) to this effect, That when they ſhould enter into the Town (not including the pleaſure of God in the buſineſſe) they ſhould not plunder any money, plate on jewels, neither kill any tame Cattell, upon pain of death.</p>
               <p>Thus may bee ſeen the Avaritious intents of ſome (more then ordinary) men, who deſire rather to heap up to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves abundance of treaſure, (enjoy fair houſes, rich Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, &amp; all things futable thereunto) then to glorifie God in their actions, making the price of bloud their Inheritance, and that before they know whether they ſhall firſt obtain, or afterward live to poſſeſſe.</p>
               <p>The chiefeſt part of the Army thus landed, gained but evill encouragement by the late Proclamation, yet (after ſome ſignals of diſcontents) on they marched in a way that directed through woods of incredible thickneſſe, receiving little or no oppoſition, except the exceſſive heat of the Sun, and intolerable drought that oppreſſed them, having not had (in many miles march) one drop of water, thoſe who took upon them to conduct the Army in the moſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious wayes and paſſages near water, proved but blinde guides, and decived them, ſo that ſome became exceeding faint, ſcantable to march, (others were neceſſitated to drink their own Urine) and all in generall ſo extreamly weakned, that it was wonderfull to behold.</p>
               <p>The Ships that landed them, ſoon after turned up to Windward unto the Generall, who continued with the Fleet plying to and again within view of the Town, only one Squadron were commanded into a Bay two leagues to the Weſtward of the Town of <hi>Domingo,</hi> whereinto a large Freſhwater River disburdeneth it ſelf; there the remnant of the Army (being three Regiments) were landed, and that within two dayes after the other, the place appointed for conjunction of both parties was at this River, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Collonell <hi>Bullard.</hi> with thoſe Regiments, (without any farther order) marched towards the Town, and (for want
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168318:8"/>of water) ſoon retreated, performing not any thing worth the memory. By this time the Land Generall with the main body of the Army came up, and after ſome ſhort refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the River, proceeded alſo towards the Town, but before they came withing three miles thereof, a ſmall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the enemy ſuddenly encountred the forlorne hope (conſiſting of 500 men) and forced them to an unſeemly retreat; the next Regiment (with ſome others) ſeconding, were alſo repulſed, and the Generall himſelf (left in a lone condition) very hardly eſcaped; the body of the Army coming up, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> at length retreated into a Fort of theirs, not far diſtant from thence, and ſome purſuing, were cut off with the great ſhot from the Fort, which was ſituate near the Sea ſide, and commanded that paſſage thorough the wood to the Town. In this exploit ſome were loſt on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, but the greateſt number ſlain were <hi>Engliſh,</hi> amongſt which Captain <hi>Cox</hi> (the chief guide for that place) was one.</p>
               <p>The Generall taking into conſideration the diſability of the Army at that time, and exceeding want of water amongſt them (there being none betwixt that and the Town, except in the former Fort, which as it was none of the ſtrongeſt fortifications, being only a plain brick wall, triangular and without flankers, yet was it furniſhed with nine piece of good Ordnance, and about 300. deſperate fellowes to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage them, and there remained little hopes that thoſe who even then received ſo much damage by leſſe then half that number (in the high-way) ſhould now ſtorm and take the place by ſudden aſſault, without eminent loſſe to the whole Army, being alſo unprovided of ladders, and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries for that purpoſe) whereupon a retreat was made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the River in the <hi>Bay,</hi> where they refreſhed with water and ſuch proviſions of victual as was daily brought on ſhore from the ſhips, preparation was alſo made for another march; a Mortar-piece was landed with <hi>Granado</hi> ſhels, and two ſmall Drakes, ſcaling Ladders were likewiſe made, but never uſed, for being too ponderous for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, they were ſent by water, and ſo to be landed in a convenient place near the town. All things being now in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168318:8"/>readineſſe (as was ſuppoſed) the 24. of <hi>April,</hi> the Army proceeded on their march, the guides promiſing to direct them in a way they had not yet known, which led to a freſh-water River, diſtant but two miles from the north part of the Town, whither they might paſſe without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of any Fort. That there was ſuch a path was known to be certain, but taking another to be it, they drew near the way they had formerly gone, advancing but ſlowly, by reaſon the Mortar-piece and ſmal Drakes (for want of horſes and furniture) the Souldiers drew by turns.</p>
               <p>The day following (before noon) they approached near the Fort (but with worſe ſucceſſe then before) for the enemy having charged the Forlorn-hope, beat then clearly to the Generals Regiment, routed thoſe alſo, execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in the backs, in as great numbers as they liſted.</p>
               <p>Major General <hi>Haines</hi> being then in the van of the Army, was moſt unworthily and ſhamefully deſerted by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, notwithſtanding that he earneſtly entreated that for Gods ſake ſome few of them would ſtand by him, if but ten in number, but ſuch was their vile cowardize and baſeneſs of ſpirit, that not one man would do it, whereupon he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed his life (amongſt the thickeſt of his enemies) at as dear a rate as became a ſtout Souldier and gallant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, who in his life time was as much beloved of his friends, as feared by his enemies, ſuch was his worthineſs, too worthy indeed to be a member of ſo Antichriſtian an Army.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> purſuing this victory, made as great a ſlaughter as they were able, and that without the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, near the one half of the Army flying before them, to the great amaze and diſcouragement of the reſt that were not as then marched up. Some having broken off the head of their launces, continued ſtil the purſuit, knocking down ſome, beating and driving others along (with their Launce ſlaves) like ſlaves and cow-hearted villains, until at length (being tired with ſlaughter, not able to proceed farther, like as the painful workman, after a laborious and hard daies labour go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to reſt) they returned to the Town, carrying with them as ſure Trophies of victory) 7. <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colours.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:168318:9"/>
               <p>The number (at this time) ſlain out right, were no leſſe then 600 men, beſides 200. more that crept into buſhes, and were left behinde in the woods, whom the <hi>Negroes</hi> and <hi>Molattoes</hi> ſoon after diſpatched; there were alſo near 300. wounded, whereof many were paſt recovery, moſt of them all receiving their hurts in the back parts. As for thoſe that did all this ſpoyle and miſchief (O miracle to believe, and ſhame to think it!) exceeded not in all the number of 50. men. The purſuit now ended, theſe running Regiments ſtood ſtill, taking op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity (with ſorrow and ſhame) to look back on their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable fellowes, groaning with wounds, &amp; weltring in bloud.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> manner of onſet was thus: After they had fired their volly of ſmal ſhot out of the woods (being aſſiſted by <hi>Negroes</hi> and <hi>Molattoes</hi>) moſt deſperately fell in and charged with their ſharp ſteel Launces, which (being directed by able bodies, and ſtrong arms) found little oppoſition of the weak and feeble multitude, parched by the heat of the Sun, and half dead with thirſt, no care being taken to ſupply this defect. The other diſadvantages were theſe. The diſ-equality betwixt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pikes and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Launces were ſuch, that the one being over long, and top-heavy, could not be managed with that dexterity, and to ſo good a purpoſe (eſpecially in narrow waies and woods) as the Launce which is about three quarters of that length; neither are the <hi>Engliſh</hi> half-pikes of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent length to reach theſe Launces; the <hi>Spaniards</hi> alſo (by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten uſe and practiſe) become more expert and ready in the uſe of theſe weapons then <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, who (although per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps old ſouldiers) never made uſe of Pike or Launce (except againſt horſe) Divers likewiſe in this expedition, that were of more valour and ſtrength then others, and would have fought, were ſo overwhelmed and trampled under foot (by the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flight of the multitude that were about them) that they were not able to make reſiſtance, but became a prey (with the reſt) unto the mercileſſe enemy. But (above all) the hand of the Almighty was much ſeen in the buſineſs, who ſtruck ſo great a terror in their hearts, that they became the people of his wrath fitted to deſtruction.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:168318:9"/>
               <p>After this ſad ſucceſſs, and lamentable loſſe, the Army (that night drew up nearer the Fort, as if they intended to execute revenge upon that; and having found a convenient place with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Musket-ſhot thereof, (where the Enemy could not bring any great Gun to beare) the Pioneers cut down the trees, and made a kinde of Breaſt-worke, (ſuch as the time would permit) and there planted the Morter-piece, which being then in a readineſſe to doe execution on the Fort; ſpeedy Orders were given to mount it on another Carriage, (fit to be drawn off) and to burn that: which being performed, (and the Granado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhells buried under ground) the Army began their march back to the old Watring-place in the Bay. But what ground there was for this action, or what the reall intent of the thing ſignified, let thoſe determine who have power to puniſh offences and reward deſerts.</p>
               <p>In this mean ſeaſon the Generall of the Navy (with divers Ships) anchored in the Road at ſuch a diſtance as that the Forts could reach them with great ſhot, and they both the Forts and Town, and having diſcerned Parties of men paſſing to and fro without the Town, conceived them to be the Engliſh Army there encamped, and thereupon ſent in divers Boats with provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Victuall and other neceſſaries for their ſupply, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching neer the ſhore diſcovered their error, and found them to be Spaniards, who (as it ſhould ſeem) had the leiſure to caſt up out-Works) and ſo returned on board in ſafety, both going and coming underneath the Fort and bank-ſides, from danger of the ſhot, by which they manifeſtly found how good and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient a place it was to have landed an Army of men.</p>
               <p>The Army lying in the Bay (as formerly) had not that ſupply of Victuall from the Ships as before, but were neceſſitated to go abroad in Parties through the Woods to ſeek for Cattell; and oftentimes meeting with ſome few Negroes, were by them put to the rowt, and divers ſlain; others caſting away their armes betook themſelves to their heels, and ſo eſcaped the fury of theſe naked Pagans; and at ſome times, when neither men or beaſts were neer, onely the leaves of trees making ſome little noiſe, and Crabs ſtirring in the woods, poſſeſſed them with ſuch eminent fear that (leaving their Weapons behinde) they ran
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168318:10"/>over Clifts into the Sea, but at length this bold Army was grown ſo politick that they would no more adventure into the woods amongſt theſe Cow-killers, (whoſe ſable deformities had often ſtrook as great a terrour in their hearts, as <hi>Pluto</hi> and all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall rowt could doe, had they been there preſent to have tortured them) exerciſing their valour onely on Horſes, Aſſe Necoes, and ſuch like, making a ſlaughter of all they met, gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily devouring skin, intrails, and all, to ſatiate their hungers; and thus were all the Troop-horſes belonging to the Army by them eaten, the Generals own hardly eſcaping; this behaviour and diet they continued for ſome daies.</p>
               <p>What number of men had been loſt in ſmall Parties, and by ſtragling (beſides at the totall rowt) was not known, untill by a generall Muſter was found that of 9700 men firſt landed, there remained then onely 8000 (the Sea-Regiment included.) Many of theſe were ſick and wounded, and moſt of them faint-hearted, not fit for ſervice. To have adventured a third time with ſuch in the face of the Enemy, were an act of no leſſe raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe than madneſſe, for had the Commanders been ever ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, able and worthy (except it had pleaſed God miraculouſly to perform the Work by them alone) which could be as little expected as deſerved) theſe ſheep like Souldiers (I mean in courage, not innocence) would queſtionleſſe have left them in the lurch, experience had already ſhewn it, and too true they ſhould have found it; And again to have ſhipped this wretced rabble, not well knowing whither to go, or how to diſpoſe of them, would alſo have been the deſtruction and loſts of the whole Fleet, having proviſions for a ſhort time, for ſo great a multitude; of theſe two evils (it pleaſed Providence) that the leaſt was choſen, and a place was now thought on, abſolutely fit indeed for ſuch an Army, where they might have food without fighting, and a Land to inhabit without oppoſition, and that within ſome few dayes ſayle. This being reſolved upon, care was taken to ſhip the men; the Morter-piece, two ſmall Drakes, and two Iron Guns (which were placed in a ſmall Fortification by them made at the mouth of the River for the better ſecuring of the Watring-place.) Before the performance of theſe things, I ſhould have declared how Adjutant Generall <hi>Jackson</hi> (that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168318:10"/>great man of little courage) was caſhiered for a Coward, and the ceremony performed of breaking his Sword over his head, for example to others; but my opinion is, that if all of like nature had been ſo dealt with, there would not have been many whole Swords left in the Army.</p>
               <p>The third of <hi>May,</hi> all were ſhipped, except the bodies of 1700 men (moſt of whoſe Armes, ſeven Field-Colours, with all their honours (if any they had) there left behinde: It is alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable that as at their landing they had no oppoſition, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at their ſhipping off, the Spaniards (with their ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) rather ſhewed themſelves defenſive than offenſive, reſting content with what they had already done, ſtrongly fortifying for the future; whereas if they had taken but this laſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity (by the diſability, weakneſſe, and cowardiſe of the Army) to have charged in with two or three hundred able reſolute men (within few dayes before, or at their going off) certainly they had deſtroyed and ſpoiled the moſt part of them all, who were more willing and ready to run into the Sea, and there pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, than to oppoſe or look upon their Enemies.</p>
               <p>All the benefit or good the Army had found in this place was onely at the firſt ſome few Cattel, and a good quantity of Sugar, Part whereof they made uſe of, caſting the reſt into the River to duleifie that (ſuch was their ignorance and folly) but this ſweet diet had ſowre ſauce.</p>
               <p>The Fleet alſo recruited with freſh water out of this faire and goodly River, (whoſe golden ſands had bloudy price) And the Souldiers being all onboard (as aforeſaid) they ſet ſayle that day before the wind, and before they had performed the leaſt part of their intent or deſires.</p>
               <p>Having now briefly, but truly, related their manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and ſucceſſe on this unforrunate Iſland, it will not be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether impartinent to deſcribe the ſcituation of the Towne and Forts adjacent, with the nature and quality of the Country, which take as followeth.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168318:11"/>
               <p>THe Towne of <hi>Sancta Domingo</hi> (Metropolis of <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and Reſidence of the Spaniſh Viceroy) is ſcituate on the South ſide of the Iſland, diſtant from the Eaſtermoſt Cape or Lands end, 28 Leagues, having North Latitude, 18. deg: 28. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n: It is well watred (and in ſome ſort ſtrengthened) by a great River which paſſeth neere the North Eaſt part thereof, at the Mouth of this River is a Harbour, which although of no great Magnitude, yet capable of entertaining Ships of good burden, The entrance to the Harbor is through a Bay of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable latitude, where there is good Anchorage, and a Road for Ships, on the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd ſide going in, is a Fort ſtrengthned with 12, or more good Guns which commandeth the Harbor and Southweſt ſide of the Towne, the other parts thereof (on the Land ſide) have for their defence an old ruinated Wall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed thick with Limetrees, which is (now lately) well repaired, and ſtrongly fortified. Within one miles Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Towne, is open ground and plaine Fields, or S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanars as they there call them, being made by induſtry and Art as are all their wayes and paſſages through the Woods, and Fields for Sugar Ganes, with other open places for husbandry, the whole Land being naturally over-growne and Covered over with trees, amongſt which of Limon, Orange, Coco, Cabage, Palmeeto, Cedar, Maſtick and <hi>Lignum vitae</hi> trees, there are good plenty.</p>
               <p>About two miles to the Weſtward of the Towne, (and neere the Bay ſide) is placed another Fort, the deſcription whereof, as alſo the dammage it did the Army in their march towards the Towne, I have already declared.</p>
               <p>Four miles farther to the Weſt from thence, is that River and Bay formerly ſpoken of, where the Army encamped, and the Fleet tooke in freſh water, which place the Spaniards had not then forfeited, but it is to be ſuppoſed that in the ſtrengthening of that (and all places elſe of conſequence, in the Weſt-Indies) they have not ſince been negligent.</p>
               <p>The commodities theſe Rivers afford (beſides the goodneſſe of their Water) conſiſts in the divers ſorts of dainty Fiſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in abounding, as alſo pieces of Gold mineralls, waſhed from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168318:11"/>forth of their bankes at certaine times, together with S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd-gold, a ſmall quantity whereof was found by ſome Engliſh Soldiers; The diſcommodities theſe Streames engender, are Allegators, which farther up in the Countrey are in too great plenty.</p>
               <p>The whole Land, (except ſome Hills of great aſcent) is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly very fruitfull, which although it produce not ſuch Fruits and Corne as doth <hi>England</hi> and other more temperate Climats (the ſcorching heat of the Sun depriving it of that happineſſe) yet of Sugar Canes, Oranges, Lemmons, Bonanoes, Bonuiſt, Planrans, Pine-Apples, Puttato, and Caſſadra Roots (whereof they make their bread) with divers other Roots and Fruits, there is no ſcarſity.</p>
               <p>It is alſo repleniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with ſtore of Oxen, and Cowes of good magnitude, as well wilde as tame. Sheep there are ſome, not many, and abundance of Hogs, and faire Horſes, which laſt are there of little uſe or ſervice in Warre, by reaſon of the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thick Woods. But beyond all, the ineſtimable rich Mines of Gold and Silver (hidden within the bowells of that Land) maketh amends for all other defect. The North and Weſt parts of the Iſland are ſcarcely at all inhabited, except by ſome few Cowkillers, Rogues that have been thither baniſhed for Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or ſome other villany, who make it their labour to kill and deſtroy many Cattell, and that onely for their Tallow and Hides, which is ſent in, to the Spaniards; At for the Towns and Villages, in the habitable parts, they are neither faire nor many, the chiefeſt whereof, I have already mentioned, which doubtleſſe (at the time of the Engliſh Armies being there) was very rich, for the neighbouring Villages and Plantations being allarumed by their Landing, they had the leiſure to convey them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with much Treaſure, Plate and I wells thither, as to a place of their beſt ſtrength and refuge.</p>
               <p>And thus much of <hi>Hispaniola.</hi> The Iſland of <hi>Jamaica</hi> muſt now be the ſubject of my following diſcourſe, whither the Fleet approaching; the 7. of <hi>May,</hi> was obſerved as another day of Humiliation, for all ſuch, whom hunger, thirſt, and the Sword of the Enemy, had not yet given a feeling ſenſe of their preſumptuous wickedneſſe, and diſobedience towards God.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168318:12"/>And conſidering the great cowardiſe that had lately poſſeſſed them, it was alſo proclaimed to the whole Army, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhould be found to turne his back to the Enemy, and run away, the next Officer (that brought up the rear of that Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) ſhould immediately run him through, which if he failed to performe, himſelf was to ſuffer death without mercy. Which ſtrict order, might have wrought better effect at <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> there being little probability of engaging with an Enemy in this place.</p>
               <p>The 9. of <hi>May</hi> they drew nigh the Iſland, and having ſailed about 16. Leagus within the South ſide thereof, the day following came to an Anchor in a ſpatious Harbour, called alſo <hi>Jamaica,</hi> where there was good Ground, and deep Water, and Manning all their ſmall Veſſells and Boats with Soldiers, ſoon landed the Army in a Bay, that lay yet farther within the Harbour, and that without the loſſe of one man, for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> having onely three or four ſmall and ſlight Breſt-workes, with ſome few Guns, and ſeeing ſo numerous an Army in readineſſe to Land, made not many ſhot, but fled in haſt to the Town of <hi>Oriſtano,</hi> which was altogether unfortified, and diſtance from thence ſix Engliſh miles, from whence they conveied away all things of value and concernment, together with their Families, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted farther into the Countray, for ſuch was their weakneſſe, and diſability for reſiſtance, that their whole number (on that part of the Iſland) exceeded not 500. Men, beſide ſome <hi>Negro</hi> ſlaves, but what they could not act by force of Armes, they did by policy, as too ſoon will appeare.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh Army being poſſeſſed of the Breſt-works, and Guns that commanded the landing-place; A Forlorne hope was drawn forth, and ſent towards the Town, who that night would not adventure to enter therein, untill the morrow fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, at which time they found it deſtitute of Inhabitants, or any thing elſe neceſſary for their entertainment, or accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, except bare walls, bedſteds, chaires, and Cow-hides; Soon after the Generall with the whole Army, (conſiſting of about 7000 men) marched up thither, where there then came in divers Spaniards (which ſeemed to be of quality) to treat, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them (as preſents for the Generall) Wine, Poultry,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168318:12"/>divers ſorts of Fruits, and other rarities that the Countrey yeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) promiſing alſo to ſend in Beaves ſufficient for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Army, with other large overtures, and high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements.</p>
               <p>This Treaty being continued for certain daies, the Enemy had free egreſſe and regreſſe aſwell into the Town, and Engliſh Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as elſwhere, continuing their welcomed preſents, bringing Cattell for the uſe of the Army, and behaving themſelves with ſuch civill and kinde (although feigned) deportment, that they invited divers Souldiers of the Army to viſit them in their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, where they had Wine given them, and were much made of; by which means they gained knowledge (by ſome overcome with Liquor) that they had been at <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and how they were there dealt withall, as alſo the extremities and wants they were driven to in their marches, for want of water and other neceſſaries in thoſe hot Countreys, whereby they were much diſabled: The Spaniards underſtanding this, and viewing the preſent weak condition of the Army, (by which they gueſſed at the future, if their wants were not ſupplied from time to time) were now animated to put in practice their uttermoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for preſervation of their goods and eſtates, and not to ſtand to any Articles of agreement, to depart the Iſland, with ſome few clothes onely to their backs (as was expected) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they fairly diſſembled the matter, and to avoid all ſuſpition, ſent their Governour (as they pretended) an old de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit Segnior, full of the French diſeaſe, and brought in betwixt two in a Hammack) to ſigne the Articles of Agreement, which he (with ſome others) accordingly did.</p>
               <p>In this meane ſeaſon, theſe ſubtill and ſlye Spaniards had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed farre away in the Woods, all their riches and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt goods, which (in ſome dayes after the Army was poſſeſſed of the Towne) remained in the Spaniſh quarters neere at hand) and might have been ſoone intercepted, they alſo gathered up all the ableſt and beſt Horſes (during the Treaty) as well in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh quarters, as their owne, and the time-limited for their departure from the Iſland (according to to the Articles ſigned) being neere expired, they drove away moſt of all the Cartell neere the Towne, and following after their Goods, Wives,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168318:13"/>Children, and ſervants (which were gone before at leaſt three dayes Journey) ſwept and cleared the Countrey as they went of all vitall proviſions, leaving their old pockie Governour as a Hoſtage for their return.</p>
               <p>And thus were they overcome by the ſubtilty and deceit of the Spaniards at <hi>Jamaica,</hi> aſwell as they had been lately van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed by their Launces at <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> and all the redreſſe that could be now thought on, was to ſend a Party in purſuit after them; Colonel <hi>Bullard,</hi> (with 2000 men) was imployed on the buſineſſe, part of which number were ſhipped in ſmall veſſels and ſhallops, and ſo conveyed by water unto a Bay (17 legues to the Eaſtward of that where the fleet lay) where they came in conjunction with the reſt that had marched thither on foot, The politick intent of this grand deſigne being to ſurpriſe the Spaniards and their luggage (betwixt both parties) as they were ſhipping off for the Main, which was ſuppoſed would be at that place, but in that they deceived themſelves, for the Enemy had no ſuch intent, but rather directed their paſſage through by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, thick woods, and over high hills, and large Mountains, (of which there are plenty) having Scouts and Sentinels abroad in each paſſible way and path, to diſcover the approach of any, It being almoſt an impoſſible thing for an Army (except well acquainted with the Countrey) to follow or finde them out, and again, the exceſſive heat of the Sun, the want of water in many places, with other defects and impediments naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the place, and diſagreeing to Engliſh conſtitutions, more enweakeneth and diſables them in ten miles march there, than forty in their own Countrey. But I ſhall now leave this purſuing party, to wander in the woods awhile, and there kill Cattell (if any they finde) to preſerve life, rather than hazard it at ſo great diſadvantages againſt the Spaniards) and ſhew in what poſture and condition thoſe in the Town were in, who (after the departure of the Spaniſh Cators) were in ſo great want that Dogs and Cats was the beſt part of their diet, with ſuch ſort of food as they had formerly taſted at <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> as Horſes, Aſſe Necoes, and ſuch like, there being ſtrict order that on pain of death none ſhould preſume to kill any Cowes or Oxen, and if at any time there went forth (by eſpeciall order)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168318:13"/>ſome ſmall party that brought in Beeves, they were diſtributed amongſt the ſuperiour Officers of the Army, the Inferiour men having onely inferiour meat, the often uſe whereof made them ſomewhat participate of the nature of the Beaſts, ſometimes living the life of Dogs, and at other times bearing the burthen of Aſſes, and what other encouragement or comfort could they have, than to ponder in their mindes, thus, <hi>Solamen miſeris ſocios habuiſſe dolores.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Jamaica</hi> Harbor, <hi>May</hi> the 24.</head>
                  <p>It was reſolved (at a Councell of Warre) That the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Navy, and Reer-Admirall, in the Ships <hi>Swiftſure</hi> and <hi>Panagon</hi> (with moſt of the Flemmiſh ſhips) ſhould return for <hi>England,</hi> Orders being given for their ſpeedy fitting, and recruit with freſh water and other neceſſaries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>May</hi> the 25.</head>
                  <p>There hapned an ill accident in the Fleet, the ſhip called the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery</hi> (of the States) a veſſell of good force and burthen, was unhappily fired by f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ling brandy wine in the Steward-room, the flame of the candle taking hold of that combuſtible liquor, ſo vehemently increaſed the fury of the fire, that there was no prevention. Wherefore (to avoid further danger) moſt of the ſhips boats that could be had in readineſſe, towed her off on a bank of ſand ſome diſtance from the Fleet, where (after ſhe had conſumed about four howres) her Magazine of powder blew up, and did no more harm; the ſhip <hi>Swiftſure</hi> being then ready to carreen, had moſt of her beſt Guns there onboard, which were all afterward (by induſtry and art) taken up, notwithſtanding that they lay in above three fathome water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>June</hi> the 1.</head>
                  <p>Colonell <hi>Bullard</hi> (after a long march to little purpoſe) retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his party to the Town, bringing with him ſome Cattel, and giving notice of great abundance that are in the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote parts of the Countrey; ſince which time there hath gon forth divers Parties, who have alſo brought in Droves of Cattell,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168318:14"/>and amongſt the reſt a Spaniſh Lady (with ſome Attendants) who were ſhe but as good as great, as virtuous as ponderous, and as fair as fat, certainly ſhe would farre exceed any three La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>England</hi> in worth, weight, and beauty.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>June</hi> the 6.</head>
                  <p>The ſhip <hi>Cardiffe</hi> ſet ſaile for <hi>England,</hi> as the Harbinger of the reſt of the Fleet which were to follow after.</p>
                  <p>And the 9th following, a generall Muſter was taken of the Land Army, whoſe number was found to be much diminiſhed of late, not ſo much by any peſtilentiall or violent diſeaſe, as for meer want of naturall ſuſtenance, which in common reaſon may ſeem ſtrange that (of all men) Souldiers ſhould ſtarve in a Cooks ſhop (as the ſaying is) or periſh for want of food in a Countrey ſo abounding with Fleſh, Fiſh, and other vitall proviſions; but it is to be hoped that for the future they may have an allowance of better and more wholſome diet than yet they have had, if the tyranny of their Commanders (or ſlothfulneſſe of themſelves, or both) prevent not.</p>
                  <p>There lately arrived at <hi>Jamaica</hi> divers Victualers with provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for the Fleet, alſo Armes and Ammunition for the Army, but Hoes and Haſchets were more ficter for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>June</hi> the 20.</head>
                  <p>There came in hither three ſmal Veſſels (Prizes) which were taken by the <hi>Selby</hi> and <hi>Grantham</hi> Frigots (who were ordered to lie plying to and agen off the Iſland of <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi>) ſome Spaniards (in them taken) reported that at the firſt appearance of the Engliſh Fleet before the Town of <hi>Domingo,</hi> the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants deſerted the place, and went all into the woods (where they continued three daies). leaving their Magazine of powder behinde, which they had once intended to have blown up, but perceiving that in that time neither the ſhips approached the Harbor (which they much dreaded) nor any elſe came to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them, they re-entred the Town, and being much encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and ſtrengthned by thoſe of the Countrey (who daily came in thither) fortified what they might, and blocking up the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168318:14"/>mouth of their Harbour with ſome Veſſels which they there ſunk, reſolved to uſe their uttermaſt undeavours to maintain the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Oristano, June</hi> the 24.</head>
                  <p>There was this day a rumour that Generall <hi>Venables</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life, which was but a rumour not reall; but his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency hath not been currant ſince his being at <hi>Hiſpaniola.</hi> The grand buſineſſe that the Army is now upon, is to ſettle each Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment in their ſeverall Quarters, where they have parcels of Land equally aproportioned unto them, which being ſubdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded amongſt the Officers, (according to their reſpective pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) ſome ſmall ſhare is like to fall unto the Common Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; but what improvement may be made thereof, or how it wil pleaſe Almighty God farther to deale with this Army, let time and truth manifeſt; the good hand of Providence having taken me from amongſt them, that ſo (according to my earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires) I might no longer be a ſpectator or recorder of their actions. I ſhall therefore now conclude, only including brief deſcription of the Iſland of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> by comparing it (in divers reſpects) with <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> together with ſome few paſſages by the way homeward.</p>
                  <p>The Iſland of <hi>Jamaica</hi> is ſcituate betwixt the Main, and the Iſle <hi>Cuba,</hi> diſtant from the one 96. Leagues, and from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 20, the center whereof lyeth directly in the ſame Lat: with the Town of <hi>Sancta Domingo</hi> (in <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi>) already deſcribed, and hath Longitude Weſt from thence, 2 deg: 18. Min: It's magnitude, is ſcantly one 3. of the ſaid Iſlands being in length 46, and breadth 14. Leagues. Notwithſtanding for the quality and quantity of Land, it is no leſſe fruitfull, and altogether as plentifull in Fiſh, Fowle, and Cattell of all ſorts; It is more Mountainous and leſſe Woody, Rivers there are divers, but the Spring-heads of ſome ariſing from Copper Mines, the Water is ſomewhat unholſome, and unſavory, unleſſe corrected by boyling (which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> uſed.) Its chiefeſt defects and impediments are theſe. It produceth not any Mynes of Gold and Silver, as doth <hi>Hispaniola</hi> and other parts of the Indies. It is alſo ill ſcituated for Traffique, lying ſuch a diſtance to Leeward
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168318:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168318:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:168318:16"/>that it is a moſt difficult thing for veſſells to turne up ſo farre to Windward as to get cleare of the Iſlands and Rocks, and are therefore neceſſitated to make their paſſage thorough the Gulfe of <hi>Florida,</hi> which is accounted dangerous, except at ſome ſeaſons of the yeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>June</hi> the 25.</head>
                  <p>The Fleet bound for <hi>England,</hi> ſet ſaile from <hi>Iamaica,</hi> Vice-Admirall <hi>Goodſon</hi> (in the <hi>Torrington</hi> Frigot) being left Admirall of that Squadron, ordered to remaine in the Indies, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of all the Engliſh Frigots of this Fleet, alſo three of the beſt ſayling <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Ships, which compleated the number of 12 ſayle, beſides victualers and prizes there remaining.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>July</hi> the 8.</head>
                  <p>The Fleet gained the length of <hi>Cape</hi> St. <hi>Anthonia</hi> (being the Weſtermoſt Cape of the Iſle <hi>Cuba</hi>) and the thirteenth <hi>Foll:</hi> they plying to Windward (having a freſh gale Eaſterly) came neer under the Tropick, and ſhort of the Cape of <hi>Florida,</hi> about thirty Leagues, where there hapned another ſad diſaſter. The <hi>Paragon</hi> Navy (a Ship of the ſecond ranke, and (at that time Reare-Admirall) took ſire, and conſumed to her Powder-room, and ſo blew up, the Reare-Admirall <hi>Dakins</hi> (and ſome others) with much danger and difficulty eſcaped, divers Ships Boats, (which were neereſt) coming in to their aſſiſtance, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there periſhed about one hundred and forty Men. By what meanes this lamentable accident was firſt occaſioned, is not yet certainly knowne, but too certaine it is, that the chiefe neglect was in the Stewards rooms, from whence the fire brake forth, violently encreaſing (paſt remedy) as the people were aſſembled together at Divine Exerciſe in the forenoon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>July</hi> the 19.</head>
                  <p>Having hitherto had (the Weather variouſly inclined) many calmes, and ſome ſtormes, with diverſity of Winds (but all of ſhort continuance) the Fleet now entred the Gulfe of <hi>Florida,</hi> and the 22 <hi>Foll:</hi> paſſed forth of the ſame, the extent thereof
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168318:16"/>being (in length) from the Cape of <hi>Florida</hi> to the uttermoſt Iſlands North of <hi>Cuba</hi> 68 Leagues, and in breadth from thoſe Iſlands to the main 20 Leagues, the current there ſetting N:N:E. the ſwiftneſſe or flackneſſe whereof dependeth on the falling of the Raines, (which about the Month of <hi>Auguſt</hi> are conſtantly very great) many exceeding large <hi>American</hi> Rivers (being aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented thereby) the ſpacious Bay of <hi>Mexico,</hi> becomes their receptacle, and ſo disburtheneth its ſwelling Floods, through this narrow ſtrait, into the <hi>Virgivian</hi> Ocean, it is therefore of ſome called the Gulfe of <hi>Mexico,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 4.</head>
                  <p>The Fleet gained the length of the <hi>Barmudas,</hi> ſince when (for the generality) being favoured with faire Windes and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable weather. The 22. of this inſtant, they had alſo the length of the Weſterne Iſlands.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 30.</head>
                  <p>They diſcried the Engliſh Shore (neer <hi>Lyzard</hi>) and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſtrong gale <hi>S. S. W.</hi> the day following, the Fleet Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at <hi>Spithead,</hi> (neer <hi>Portsmouth.</hi>) three ſayle having been ſeparated from the reſt by obſcure weather in the night (before their entrance into the Gulfe) came in hither alſo this day, ſome few houres before the other.</p>
                  <p>And now for ever bleſſed be the Divine Creator, who hath dealt thus mercifully with us, the unworthieſt of his Servants, giving us ſo large experience of his abundant goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and bringing us once more unto the Land of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity. The Lord in mercy ſo encline the hearts of this Nation, that thoſe grand ſinnes of Preſumption and Covetouſneſſe, may no longer reigne amongſt them, leſt ſeaking after ſhadows, they loſe the reall ſubſtance; or coveting the good or Gold of others, they incurre the high diſpleaſure of Almighty God upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo become the ſcorne and deriſion of their Enemies, and a by-word to other Nations. <hi>Avertas Deus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
